When you interact with these models,
naturally they don't
remember what you say
before or any of
the previous conversation, which
is an issue when you're building
some applications like
Chatbot and you
want to have a conversation with
them.
And so, in this section we'll
cover memory, which is basically how
do you remember previous parts of
the conversation and feed that into
the language model so that they
can have this
conversational flow as you're interacting
with them.
So, LangChain offers multiple
sophisticated options of
managing these memories. Let's
jump in and take a look.
So, let me start off by importing my
OpenAI API key,
and then let me import
a few tools that I'll need.
Let's use as the motivating
example for memory, using
LangChain to manage a chat
or a chatbot conversation.
So, to do that, I'm
going to set the LLM
as a chat interface of
OpenAI with temperature equals 0,
and I'm going to use
the memory as a
ConversationBufferMemory,
and you'll
see later what this means.
And I'm
going to build a conversation chain. Again,
later in this short course, Harrison
will dive much more
deeply into what exactly
is a chain in LangChain. So, don't
worry too much about the details of
the syntax for now,
but this builds an LLM.
And if I start to have a conversation,
conversation.predict, give
the input,
Hi, my name is Andrew.
Let's see what it says.
Hello, Andrew, it's
nice to meet you. Right? And
so on. And then,
let's say I ask it,
what is 1 plus 1?
1 plus 1 is 2, and then
ask it again, you know, what's
my name?
Your name is Andrew,
as you mentioned earlier. Hmm,
there's a little bit of
trace of sarcasm there,
not sure.
And so if you want,
you can change this
verbose variable to true,
to see what LangChain is actually doing.
When you run predict,
Hi my name is Andrew,
this is the prompt
that LangChain is generating.
It says,
the following is a
friendly conversation between a
human and an AI. AI is talkative,
and so on. So this is a
prompt that LangChain has generated
to have the system have
a hopeful and friendly conversation,
and it has to save the conversation,
and here's the response.
And when you
execute this on the
second and third parts of the
conversations,
it keeps the prompt as follows.
And notice that by the time I'm
uttering, what is my name? This
is the third turn, that's my
third input.
It has stored the current conversation
as follows. Hi, my name is Andrew,
what is 1 plus 1,
and so on. And so this memory
or this history of
the conversation gets longer
and longer. In fact, up on top,
I have used the memory
variable to store the memory.
So if I were to print memory.buffer,
it has stored
the conversation so far.
You can also print this out, memory.loadMemoryVariables.
The
curly braces here is
actually an empty dictionary. There's
some more advanced features that
you can use with
a more sophisticated input, but we
won't talk about
them in this short course. So don't worry
about why there's an empty curly braces
here.
But this is what LangChain has
remembered in the memory of the
conversation so far. It's
just everything that the AI or
that the human has said.
I encourage you to pause
the video and run the code.
So, the way that
LangChain is storing
the conversation is with this
ConversationBufferMemory.
If I were to use the
ConversationBufferMemory
to specify a couple of
inputs and outputs,
this is how you add
new things to the memory
if you wish to do so explicitly.
Memory.saveContext says, hi, what's up?
I know this is
not the most exciting conversation,
but I wanted to have a short example.
And with that,
this what the status of the memory is.
And once again,
let me actually show the
memory variables. Now,
if you want to add additional
data to the memory, you can keep
on saving additional context. So,
conversation goes on, not much,
just hanging, cool.
And if you print out the memory,
you know, there's
now more stuff in it.
So when you use
a large language model
for a chat conversation,
the large language model
itself is actually stateless.
The language model itself does not
remember the conversation you've
had so far. And each transaction, each
call to the API
endpoint is independent.
And chatbots appear to have memory
only because there's
usually
rapid code that provides
the full conversation that's
been had so far as context to the LLM.
And so,
the memory can store explicitly
the terms or the utterances so far.
Hi, my name is Andrew. Hello, it's
just nice to meet you and so on.
And this memory storage
is used as input
or additional context to the LLM
so that they can generate
an output as if it's
just having the next
conversational turn,
knowing what's been said before.
And
as the conversation becomes long,
the amounts of
memory needed becomes really,
really long and does the
cost of sending a lot
of tokens to the LLM,
which usually charges based
on the number of tokens it needs to
process,
will also become more expensive.
So LangChain provides several
convenient kinds of memory to store
and accumulate the conversation.
So far, we've been looking at
the ConversationBufferMemory.
Let's
look at a different type of memory.
I'm going to import the
conversation buffer window
memory that only keeps
a window of memory. If I set memory
to conversational buffer window
memory with k equals one,
the variable k equals one specifies
that I wanted to remember just
one conversational exchange.
That is one utterance from
me and one utterance from
chatbot. So,
now if I were to have it save context,
hi, what's up, not much,
just hanging.
If I were to
look at memory.load variables, it
only remembers the most recent utterance.
Notice it's dropped. Hi, what's up?
It's just saying
human says not much, just hanging,
and the AI says cool. So that's
because k was equal to one.
So this is a
nice feature because it
lets you keep track
of just the most
recent few conversational terms.
In practice, you probably won't
use this with k equals one. You
use this with k set
to a larger number.
But still, this prevents the
memory from growing
without limit as
the conversation goes longer.
And so if I were to
rerun the conversation that
we had just now,
we'll say, hi, my name is Andrew.
What is 1 plus 1?
And now I ask it,
what is my name?
Because k equals 1,
it only remembers the
last exchange versus what
is 1 plus 1?
The answer is 1 plus 1 equals 2,
and it's forgotten this early exchange
which is now, now says, sorry,
don't have
access to that information.
One thing I hope you
will do is pause the video,
change this to true in
the code on the left,
and rerun this conversation
with verbose equals true,
and then you will
see the prompts actually
used to generate this,
and hopefully you'll
see that the memory,
when you're
calling the LLM on what is my name,
that the memory has
dropped this exchange where
it learned what is my name,
which is why it now says it doesn't
know what is my name.
With the conversational token
buffer memory,
the memory will limit the
number of tokens saved.
And because a lot of
LLM pricing is based on
tokens, this maps more directly
to the cost of the LLM calls. So,
if I were to say the
max token limit is equal to 50,
and actually let me
inject a few comments. So let's
say the conversation is, AI
is what? Amazing.
Backpropagation is what? Beautiful.
Chatbot is what? Charming.
I use ABC as the first letter of
all of these conversational terms.
We can keep track of what was said
when.
If I run this with a high token limit,
it has almost the whole conversation.
If I increase the token limit to
100,
it now has the whole conversation,
sign of AI is what?
If I decrease it,
Then, you know, it chops off
the earlier parts
of this conversation to retain the
number of tokens
corresponding to the
most recent exchanges
but subject to not exceeding the
token limit.
And in case you're wondering why we needed
to specify an LLM, it's because
different LLMs use
different ways of counting tokens, so
this tells it to use the
way of counting tokens that the
chatOpenAI
LLM uses.
I encourage you to pause
the video and run the code,
and also try modifying the
prompt to see if you
can get a different output.
Finally, there's one last type of memory
I want to illustrate here, which
is the conversation
summary
buffer
memory.
And the idea is, instead of limiting
the memory to a fixed number
of tokens based on the most
recent utterances or a fixed number
of conversational exchanges,
let's use an LLM
to write a summary
of the conversation so far,
and let that
be the memory.
So here's an example where I'm going
to create a long
string with someone's schedule, you
know, there's meeting at 8am
with your product team, you need your PowerPoint
presentation, and so on and
so on. So there's a
long string saying what's
your schedule, you know, maybe
ending with a noon
lunch at the Italian
restaurant with a customer, bring
your laptop, show
the latest LLM demo.
And so, let me use a
conversation summary buffer memory
with a max token limit
of 400 in this case,
pretty high token limit,
and I'm going to
insert in
a few conversational terms in
which we start with hello, what's
up, no one's just hanging,
cool.
And then
what is on the schedule today,
and the
response is, you know,
that long schedule.
So this
memory
now has quite a lot of text in it.
In fact, let's take a look
at the memory variables.
It contains that entire
piece of text,
because 400 tokens was sufficient
to store
all this text.
But now,
if I were to reduce the max token limit,
say to 100 tokens,
remember, this stores the
entire conversational history.
If I reduce the number of tokens
to 100,
then,
the conversation summary
buffer memory has actually used an
LLM,
the OpenAI endpoint in this case,
because that's
where we set the LLM to, to
actually generate a summary
of the conversation so far.
So the summary is, human-AI
engage in small talk before
the start of the schedule, and
informs human in the morning meeting,
blah, blah, blah,
lunch meeting with customer
interested in AI and latest
AI developments.
And so,
if we were to have a conversation,
using this LLM,
let me create a conversation chain,
same as before.
And let's say that we were to ask,
you know, input what would be
a good demo to show.
I said verbose equals true, so here's
the prompt.
The LLM thinks the current conversation
has had
this discussion so far,
because that's
the summary of the conversation.
And just one note, if you're
familiar with the OpenAI
chat API endpoint,
there is a specific system message.
In this example,
this is not using
the official OpenAI system message,
it's just including it as part
of the prompt here,
but it nonetheless works pretty well.
And given this prompt, you know,
the LLM outputs
basic constituent AI developments,
so it's just showcasing our
latest NLP capabilities. Okay, that's
cool.
Well, it's, you know, making
some suggestions to the cool demos,
and makes you think if I
was meeting a customer, I
would say,
boy, if only there were open source
framework available to
help me build cool NLP applications
using LLMs.
Good things are launching.
And the interesting thing is,
if you now look at
what has happened to the memory,
so, notice that here,
it has incorporated the
most recent AI system output,
whereas my utterance asking it,
what would be a good demo to show,
has been incorporated
into the system message, you know,
the overall summary of
the conversation so far.
With the conversation
summary buffer memory,
what it tries to do is keep the
explicit storage of the
messages up to the
number of tokens we
have specified as a limit. So,
you know, this part,
the explicit storage, we're
trying to cap at 100 tokens, because
that's what we're asked for.
And then anything beyond that,
it will use CLM to generate a summary,
which is what is seen up here.
And even though I've
illustrated these different memories
using a chat as
a running example,
these memories are useful
for other applications too,
where you might keep on
getting new snippets of text,
or keep on getting new information,
such as if your
system repeatedly goes online
to search for facts, but you want to
keep the total memory
used to store this
growing list of facts as, you know,
capped and not
growing arbitrarily long.
I encourage you to pause
the video and run the code.
In this video,
you saw a few types of memory
including buffer memories
that limits based on number of
conversation exchanges or tokens
or a memory that can
summarize tokens above a certain
limit.
LangChain actually supports additional
memory types as well.
One of the most
powerful is vector data memory,
if you're familiar with word embeddings
and text embeddings, the
vector database actually
stores such embeddings.
If you don't know what that means, don't
worry about it. Harrison will
explain it later.
And it can then
retrieve the most relevant
blocks of text using this type of a
vector database for its memory.
And LangChain also
supports entity memories,
which is applicable when
you wanted to remember
details about specific people,
specific other entities,
such as if you talk about
a specific friend,
you can have LangChain
remember facts about that friend,
which would be
an entity in an explicit way.
When you're implementing applications
using LangChain, you
can also use multiple types
of memories such as
using one of the types of
conversation memory that you saw in
this video plus
additionally entity memory
to recall individuals. So this way
you can remember maybe a summary
of the conversation
plus an explicit way of storing
important facts about
important people in
the conversation.
And of course, in addition to
using these memory types,
it's also not uncommon
for developers to
store the entire conversation in the
conventional database. Some
sort of key value store or SQL database.
So you could refer back
to the whole conversation
for auditing or for
improving the system further.
And so, that's memory types. I
hope you find this useful
building your own applications.
And now let's go on to the next
video to learn about the
key building block of LangChain, namely
the chain.